早安
我們今天會開一個新的系列
Proverbs
有沒有人讀過Proverbs
Anybody have read Proverbs before?
OK, very good
好
我們的主題是Wise up
Wise up
我們上一個系列是說什麼的?
是說什麼的?
喜樂,是不是?
我們有喜樂
這個系列我們會說Proverbs
要有智慧
Proverbs是怎樣的?
What is Proverbs like?
It is a collection of short memorable statements
是很短的一些statements
For example
Lazy hands make a man poor
Diligent hands make a man rich
如果你懶的話
你就會窮
你很diligent的話
就會有錢
這些是很practical的
Practical observation
這些是不是promises?
It doesn't mean it's 100%
不是100%
你很diligent
Automatic,是guarantee
你會有錢的
有些懶人是有錢的
可能他的家庭很有錢
That's why they are rich
It's not a guarantee
還有一些Proverbs是這樣說
Start children off by the way they should go
And even when they are old
They will not turn from it
你小時候教導小朋友
他應該怎樣走
When they are old
They will not walk away from it
是不是guarantee?
是不是guarantee你的小朋友
你教導他很好
認識主耶穌
教他聖經
他長大
是不是guarantee
他會做一個很好的基督徒?
是不是guarantee?
這個是一個observation
observation
這些Proverbs不單止有observation
這個intent
是to be
Not to be applied in every situation
But it comes rooted to God
The wisdom comes from a reverent relationship with God
這些Proverbs的basis
The basis of all the Proverbs
Is that God is creator
He is authority
And through him we can have wisdom
Ok 誰寫Proverbs的?
誰寫Proverbs的?
有沒有人知道?
Who wrote the book of Proverbs?
叫做Solomon
King Solomon
Solomon是誰?
他是一個皇帝
是嗎?
以色列好像
是David
David's son
Ok we are going to read his story
We are going to read his story
We are going to ask Vian to read
The Cantonese for us
我們一起起來
去讀神的話語
Go ahead
在基比烏耶和華夜間在夢中向所羅門顯現
對他說:你要我賜給你什麼,隨你所願求
所羅門說:耶和華我的神啊
你是你的僕人,接替我父親大衛作王
但我現在年幼,不知道怎樣出入
你的僕人在你所揀選的這些百姓中
這是一個多而不可勝數的大民族
求你賜給你的僕人一顆聰明的心
好能治理你的百姓,能分辨是非
因為誰能治理這麼大的你的百姓呢?
耶和華喜悅所羅門這樣的請求
於是神對他說:你既然求這個
沒有求長壽,也沒有求財福
甚至沒有求你受的的性命
而是求能分辨是非的智慧
我就照你所求的去做
我會賜給你一顆智慧和聰明的心
使你以前沒有過,將來也不會有這樣的人
此外,我還要賜給你
沒有的,沒有求的財富和榮耀
使你在你的一生中與其他王相比
沒有平等之人
如果你遵行我的道,謹守我的律例和命令
如同你父親大衛所行的
我就會賜給你長壽
然後所羅門醒來,發現這是一場夢
為你自己祈禱
為你祈禱
祂的神父大衛,我們今天來到你面前
在你的寺廟,你的聖堂
我們想在心中和真相中對你祈禱
你讓我們滿意,我們給你全面的關注
你讓我們滿意,我們給你全面的慈悲
神父大衛,我們今天想向你全力投入
因為你是唯一一個
值得我們關注和慈悲的人
請你今天早上給我們溫柔的心
讓我們成長在神的智慧
在耶穌的名下我們祈禱,Amen
我們一起坐下來
有沒有人,上個星期
星期五我們發了一個
Pre-Service Meditation,有沒有人看過?
有沒有人看過?
一個問題就是,如果你是Solomon
如果神問你,你想要什麼?
你會想要什麼呢?
有沒有人討論過這個問題?
沒有?
沒有討論過?
沒有人問過?
有沒有人討論過?
Stanley有沒有討論過?
哎呀,哎呀,哎呀,不要緊,不要緊
我們會提醒,我們會提醒
我們會提醒Aunt Fiona,我們會提醒Stanley
有沒有人討論過?
在你們的群組,有沒有人討論過?
Anybody? No?
歪歪他們呢?有沒有討論過?
食物,你會叫神給你多點食物?
Buffet everyday? 真的?
Solomon就問,叫神給他什麼?
叫他有智慧,Wisdom
Wisdom from the Lord
為什麼他叫神給他Wisdom?
因為他知道,他看到他爸爸是誰?
大衛,David was blessed by God
And he was a great king
他是一個很好的皇帝
然後他就像大衛一樣,跟隨他的榜樣
Follow his example
但是他是一個年輕的皇帝
他就想神給他智慧
To give him wisdom
So that he can also lead Israel
Like his father led Israel
And so what did God say?
神怎樣跟他說?
Yes, because you have not asked for riches
I will give you what you have asked for
I will give you wisdom
但要給我condition
What are the conditions?
Not only have you asked for wisdom
But because you have not asked for riches
I will give you riches also
But if you obey, I will also bless you with old age
Bless you with old age
Solomon有沒有Obey?
我們之後會看
We are going to read also proverbs
We are going to read together proverbs
Let's read the English together and proverbs
Ready, 1,2,3
The Proverbs of Solomon, son of David, king of Israel
For gaining wisdom and instruction
For understanding words of insight
For receiving instruction in prudent behavior
Doing what is right and just and fair
For giving prudence to those who are simple
Knowledge and discretion to the young
Let the wise listen and add to their learning
Let the discerning get guidance
For understanding proverbs and parables
The sayings and riddles of the wise
Solomon 寫proverbs
Solomon寫proverbs
他現在寫了這裡
是有幾個目的的
第一是去know
To know wisdom
他說什麼?
Gaining wisdom and instruction
Understanding the words of insight
去知道智慧是什麼
第二不單止是知道智慧是什麼
他想你做到
做到什麼?
做到wise things
He wants you to do wise things
他說receiving instruction in prudent behavior
For doing what is right, just and fair
他想你每天有智慧跟隨耶穌
不單止to know and to do
But it is also for the young and for the wise
第一是for the young and simple
To have knowledge and discretion
And it is also for the wise
這個proverbs是給很簡單的
還有可以給很wise的
The wise they can listen and add to their learning
To learn discerning
To the discerning get guidance
So it is for everybody
每個人都要有智慧
每個人要認識智慧是什麼
每個人都要做wise things
It is for the simple and it is for the wise
所以Solomon寫這段書
It is for everybody
Everybody to get wiser, to get smarter
And he finishes the first paragraph with the next verse
The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom
我們今天會學這個verse
What does it mean?
The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom
We are going to look at each of the words very specifically
第一個word是Lord
神,神是什麼
有幾個字
Omnipotence
Omniscience
Omnipresence
Eternality
Sorry, 我不懂得讀英文
Holiness
知道Omnipotence是什麼嗎
Anybody knows?
Omnipotence
有沒有聽過
It means the ability to do anything
神是all powerful
We believe God is all powerful
Omnipotence
第二個呢
Omniscience
有沒有人知道
It is the ability to know everything
神是什麼
All knowing
We believe God is all knowing
The next thing is
Omnipresence
神是什麼
神是everywhere
God is here with us now
He sees you on your phone
Playing video games
神是看到你的
God is everywhere
還有什麼
Eternality
God is forever
He exists forever
He is the Alpha and the Omega
The beginning and the end
And also God is holy
He is set apart from evil
He is set apart from sin
我們要明白
神是all these qualities
That is the basis of wisdom
That God is in control
He is all powerful
He knows everything
He sees you
God is the basis of wisdom
我們現在會有discussion questions
我們會分組
我想看你明白
Wisdom and knowledge 有什麼不同
What is the difference between wisdom and knowledge
接著我想你apply你的definition
在這四方面
如果你有knowledge in finance
和wisdom in finance
有什麼不同呢
What is the difference
你足球有knowledge
和足球有wisdom
What is the difference
你可以選幾個category
現在分組可以discuss
有四五分鐘
Let's discuss
OK 我訪問你們先
你們的組
你們這些女生
你覺得knowledge and wisdom 有什麼不同
你們的group definition是什麼
knowledge 是書面上的知識
但wisdom 是你解決問題的能力
你們選了什麼category
有沒有選一個category
還沒討論到
OK
Uncle Stanley的group
Hugo
What is the question
這四個是誰
不是
你選一個category
然後說什麼是wisdom
什麼是knowledge
什麼是knowledge in finance
足球
For example
knowledge in football
和wisdom in football
你講一個example
knowledge就是技巧
傳球的東西
智慧就是別人foul你
你怎樣不打他們
是一個智慧
OK interesting example
Elias 有沒有補充
我覺得智慧是tactics
可以控制訓練
我尾次的球都扭了
OK
Very good
I think a good football example is
You know how to play football
But you know when to tackle somebody
你什麼時候tackle
他在offense
人家的龍門那裡tackle人
是不是wisdom
不是
但如果你one on one
人家快要進來的時候
你要tackle
That is wisdom
So you need to know when to tackle
OK 我問這些女生
你們選了什麼category
我們選了overall
怎樣去identify between wisdom and knowledge
你share
我們覺得wisdom是一個long term
是全面一點
It includes judgment
knowledge 和你對世界的見解
And wisdom 也包括worldly wisdom
和godly wisdom
然後knowledge 大概是書本
就是看到的knowledge
但wisdom是你怎樣去內化那些knowledge
And 怎樣去用
OK All right
Very good
我們讓Nathan說一下
Nathan
Knowledge in finance
And wisdom in finance
你讀finance
你說一下你的example
我覺得可以叫Uncle Stanley補充一下
Finance knowledge
就是你怎樣去看accounting statement
怎樣去看盤數
Wisdom是你怎樣去application
In your investment
怎樣去看你的portfolio
就是可以Uncle Stanley再說多一點
OK 好
Finance是你認識金融系統怎樣運作
And then wisdom is maybe you know how to budget
You know how to budget your finances
Or you know how to make money
Right? You know how to make money
鞋呢?有沒有example?
鞋有沒有example?
鞋example是你知道什麼鞋是值錢的
And then you know when to sell it
是嗎?
You know when to sell it
是嗎? Yes
還有呢? Last example
Video games 有沒有?
Video games 有沒有example?
Anybody have a video game example?
Uncle Vincent you have a video game example of knowledge and wisdom?
不要緊 你說你那些Sega Genesis
Nintendo那些 你說
Super Mario 你說
OK Alright
Is this Pac-Man? You are eating Pac-Man?
You are always eating in Pac-Man
OK 現在我們會說What fear is not
What is fear? What fear is not?
Fear is not being terrified
Dread of a big bully paralyzing
有些人見到什麼就很害怕
Freeze在那裡 有沒有人怕蛇?
有沒有怕蛇? OK
有沒有人怕蜘蛛?
Spider or insects
有些人一見到那些蟑螂就freeze在那裡
啊 救命啊 叫媽叫爸 是不是
有沒有人是這樣?
你叫Nathan過來幫你處理
OK OK
Fear is not
The fear of the Lord 不是很恐怖
God is here
We are run away
He is gonna catch us
He is gonna eat us like Pac-Man
是不是? It is not paralyzing
還有Fear is not harsh
Judging or hiding
好像在Garden of Eden那樣
亞當 夏娃犯了罪
然後他怎樣?
他犯了罪之後怎樣?
他就有hiding
God
God就找他了 是不是?
亞當 夏娃 你在哪裡?
我找不到你 你去哪裡了?
We saw we were naked
And we were ashamed
And we were hiding
Because of our nakedness
It is not like we were hiding from God
Fear of the Lord is not hiding or judging
What is fear?
Fear 第一是Awe
Awe
這個字Awe 是
我
For example
我行山
OK Let's look at the next slide
我行山 看到一個很美的
很美的Canyon
In Iceland
And I am like in awe
Wow! This looks like Jurassic Park
是不是?
It is like so beautiful
這麼美
I am so in awe of the Lord
Because He is all powerful
He is creator
I am in awe of how majestic He is
神啊 你好偉大啊
我敬拜你
I am so in awe of who you are
You are wonderful
Psalm says this
When I look to your heavens
And the work of your fingers
The moon and the stars
You have set them in place
What is man that you are mindful of him
我記得我去尼泊爾
有沒有人去過尼泊爾
Nepal
我行一個Base Camp
叫Annapurna Base Camp
Annapurna Base Camp 好美啊
知不知道為什麼
是一個360
You walk to the mountains
And it is 360
8000m mountains all around you
你看哪裡都是雪山
是很美的
And I was in awe
Wow God
This is like the best view in the world
I was in awe
神啊 你好偉大
That you created these mountains
I was in awe
Fear of the Lord
Is in awe of how God is so amazing
第二呢
Fear of the Lord is reverence
Respect
Reverence, respect
好像一個小孩
拖著一個爸爸
跟著他去
去迪士尼
跟著他去玩
去學習
為什麼這個小孩跟著他呢
是不是因為這個爸爸
Grab 了他的手
拖他這樣走呢
不是
是因為這個小孩
是信靠他的爸爸
他的爸爸是強大
信任
榮耀
所以他拖著他爸爸的手
不是因為他爸爸拉著他
拉著他
拉著他緊緊的
不是
是因為我們信任我們的神父
他愛我們
他會指導我們
在他的智慧和知識
這就是為什麼我們榮耀他
我們尊敬他
所以Fear of the Lord
是兩個東西
我們是在神父的驕傲
第二呢
我們尊敬他
給他尊敬
他值得的東西
第三點
Fear of the Lord
是健康的理解
他的權力
和後果
是從這裏來的
這裏有個鍋
你幾歲
你意識到
你碰一個煮沸的水
是會傷害到你的
你知道嗎
你什麼時候
你意識到
是不是有些人還沒有意識到
還沒有意識到
沒關係
有些事是不用去做
才去意識到的
但是
健康的理解
權力和後果
是神創造這個世界
這個世界有一個自然的模式
自然的模式是
如果你碰到火
你會被燒
如果你
如果你喝
如果你吃太多
你會吃太飽
你不能再玩足球
這個世界有自然的模式
如果你反對自然的模式
有後果
你必須面對這些後果
所以我們需要了解
神的恐懼
是認識到神有權力
他創造了這個世界
有一定的方式
如果你反對
有後果
明白嗎?
抱歉,我要用英文來解釋這些難聽的詞語
待會你的導師會用中文來解釋
幫你解釋
如果你不明白我的英文
神的恐懼有三個方面
神的驚訝
神的尊敬和尊重
第三
明白神的權力
和後果
來自於不聽從神
我們要跟隨神
要跟隨他
要跟隨他的榮譽
要跟隨他的智慧
要跟隨他
我們要走一條死路
現在是學生的故事時間
我們邀請Vian上來
給她們掌聲
Vian我們知道
她是很投入在explorer
很投入在explorer
我們去了Cambodia
你覺得在柬埔寨
你學到什麼?
這麼有趣
在柬埔寨
我學會了舒服與不舒服
我先說中文
雖然是第一次去
我第一年去
一開始覺得很辛苦
因為我們首先坐車
我們當時五個人
塞在一輛很擠迫的車
然後車很悶熱
很熱的
很痛
因為大家都會流汗
所以首先有身體不舒服
也有心理不舒服
我們要去學校
跟小朋友去跟他們唱歌
玩耍
跟他們互動
教英文
講故事
對一個Iron來說
是非常恐怖的事
我第一次都很害怕
躲在Johnny的後面
去到最後一天
我已經完全習慣了
感受到神給我的力量
我就變得舒服與不舒服
然後我就去完第一年之後
我第二年也有再去
因為我覺得有很大的呼籲
在柬埔寨去做這個師傅
對,非常好
我們現在做學生故事
我們已經做了一個月半
你覺得我們為什麼要做學生故事?
為什麼我們要做學生的見證?
非常好的問題
我覺得除了聽教會的教導
教會的教師
他們會說聖經裡面的東西
知識
但為了得到知識
你必須要有這個經驗
如果你自己沒有經歷過
你不會直接吸收到經驗
從你的朋友
身邊的大人
你的教導
你的家人
但如果是朋輩之間
我會覺得在我的信仰裡
好像很孤單
或者我不知道怎麼走
我這麼小,我能做什麼?
我慢慢會想出來
但我身邊的人
有經歷一些我可以從中學到的東西
或者我能啟發到自己
有這樣的想法
或者有這樣的反思
非常好
我們想你們去理解
學生也被神改變
Viann, YY, Aaron, Nathan
他們是基督徒
他們也收到聖靈
我們相信聖靈也在教導他們
所以我們可以從神的教導中學到
從聖靈的教導中學到
不是因為教徒太懶
不想說話
不想說太久
不是的,是因為我們想看到
神的教導
從彼此學到
因為神為我們建立了教會
為我們建立了家庭
學習,支持,鼓勵彼此
這就是我們有學生的故事
Viann,你讀《諸侯傳》的時候
你覺得神在教導你什麼?
我講我的主要想法之前
不如我講一個故事
學生的故事
我講一個我之前經歷到
什麼是真正的尊敬和恐懼
就是神的尊敬
首先有兩個背景
我中學的時候的數學很差
我的數學是很差的
我又差,因為我一開始就懶
我本來也不太懂
我只是不太懂
我很緊張
緊張到晚上做夢
我也是在做數學
我不知道你們有沒有聽過
我最討厭做數學
我最差的就是做數學
我會做夢做數學
整件事很恐怖
夜夢
可能隔幾天就會做數學
做夢,所以很緊張
第二就是我之前中學時經常頭暈
我不知道為什麼
我不知道是不是緊張
但我覺得沒有什麼關係
可能那天我很開心
沒有什麼事要做
我一起床就會很頭暈
頭暈幾個小時
通常我八點起床
到十點多就會沒有頭暈
也會幾個小時
會令我頭暈
但我從來沒有解釋為什麼
總之這兩個是很重要的背景
故事就是
我之前有一個測試
我忘記考什麼
總之是數學測試
我又很緊張
但這次我有一點不同
因為我之前考得一般般
未至於失敗
但也很接近失敗的邊緣
我努力溫習
我真的有勤力一點操作
去做數學
這次我比其他考試更有信心
考之前我還可以早睡
我通常已經算早
我十一點多睡
我記得我是健康中學
十一點多
我當晚十點半就睡了
我記得我睡前
我媽媽叫我祈禱
因為她知道我有測試
我媽叫我祈禱
通常我都會祈禱
但我記得那次
我沒有跟她說
我只是敷衍了
平時都是這樣
但那晚我還想
我祈禱也沒有用
每次都只是一般般
那次我沒有祈禱
隨便吧
我去了考試
那天起床
沒有頭暈
我準備好了
我對數學好像很熟悉
我坐下
打開試卷
我立即開始頭暈
暈到傻
我看著試卷
數字在跳來跳去
我看到我眼前的數字
我看不到任何東西
我心想我的天啊
那一刻很害怕
因為那次的測試
算是比較有信心的一次
但我一坐下就頭暈
我就在想
我就覺得
GG了
最後我媽媽應該不知道
但我這次的測試是失敗了
我媽媽很驚訝
我沒有跟任何人說
這也是我中學唯一失敗過的
唯一或其中一個
我忘記了
你當作是其中一個失敗的
我失敗過的測試
經過了整件事之後
我收了試卷
我覺得你可以做幾件事
你可以說
我失敗了
但我又坐下去反思
我發現
這不是一個巧合
因為我都說了
我平時頭暈
我的模式是早上暈
然後就會慢慢消失
但那天我暈了
我突然打開墨丸就開始暈
是一個很恐怖的事件
所以我知道
這不是一個巧合
是一個後果
因為我前一晚就想
我可以了
不需要祈禱
平時祈禱也沒什麼用
我這次有溫書
我一定可以
但我最後都失敗了
所以是一個後果
是一個教訓
讓我學習
當時如果我沒有反思
我就不會有這個新的恐懼
因為經過了整件事之後
我真的學會了
凡事都是神掌控的
即使你有多失控
你對自己有信心的話
你靠自己是不行的
因為最後掌控一切的
都是神
可能你打一場球賽前
很有信心
可能你突然在街上跌倒
就沒有了
跌倒了
我就會
我不知道為什麼這麼開心
你也踢不長一球
所以這些很小的事
這些全部我相信都不是巧合
都是提醒我
神是最終掌管的人
也是連接今天的主題
Wisdom
敬畏的
是智慧的開端
當我開始有對神的敬畏
In all that he is the one that is control
And respect of his authority
And respect that he is the one in control
And respect that my actions will have consequences
所以經過這次的經歷之後
我就掌了智慧
不可以靠自己就要靠神
哇,讓我們給她掌聲
非常好,Vian
非常好,謝謝
OK
我們要再進行一個課程
這個恐懼是如何的
是智慧的開始
第一點是知識的基礎
If you don't have the fear of the Lord
You will not have the foundation of knowledge
驕傲的人呢
你學不學到東西
驕傲的人學不學到東西
驕傲的人會不會學東西
有沒有人是很驕傲的
覺得他什麼都厲害
The proud cannot learn
They think that they are the best already
They think they are above all
They can't learn from anybody
如果你驕傲呢
You do not have the foundation of knowledge
So the fear of the Lord is the foundation of knowledge
神啊,我不懂,我不懂做
我Math不懂做
神啊,我不知道我去哪個方向好
我大學去哪
我不知道我和男朋友女朋友的關係
怎麼處理
神啊,你可不可以給我智慧
I don't know what to do
And that is the foundation of knowledge
The fear of the Lord is the foundation of knowledge
We don't know
But we know who knows
Who knows
God knows
And so we trust him
That is the foundation of knowledge
大義,the lens of truth
When we start with the fear of the Lord
All knowledge falls in its proper place
Science is the discovery of God's handiwork
我們認識神
Is in control
Omnipotent, omnipresent
All powerful, all knowing
Everywhere, eternal, holy
When we recognize that God is the truth
God is truth, Jesus is truth
耶穌說什麼
我是真理
I am the truth, the life and the way
No one comes to the father except through me
So when we recognize that Jesus is the truth
Then we will begin to truly have wisdom
And the last thing is
Fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom
Because it leads to life and freedom
真正的,真正的,life and freedom
When we think
It says the fear of the Lord leads to life
And whoever has it rests satisfied
When we fear God
When we stand in awe of him
Reverence of him
Align our lives with his reality
We are free from the fear of anything else
我們認識神是在控制的
We don't have to fear anything else
We believe God is in control
He is all powerful
他會照顧我們的生命
We don't have to fear anything else
We recognize he is all powerful
他會看顧我們的
He will take care of us
So then that is why
This is the fear
The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom
Because it leads to true life and true freedom
如果你是基督徒
你相信主耶穌是為了你而死的
你是你的個人救主
Do you need to fear death?
誰怕死的?
如果你是真正認識主耶穌是你的救主
You don't fear death anymore
You have true freedom and you have true life
Because Jesus died for you
So you do not have to have the eternal death
你明白嗎?
You have eternal life
Not eternal death
The fear of the Lord is the beginning of true life
Eternal life and eternal freedom
So how do we have
How do we have fear of Lord
That gives true life and true wisdom
我們看四樣東西
It is the last slide I think
The first thing is we need to recognize Jesus
Recognize God
Are we in awe of God?
Are we respecting Him in reverence?
Do we recognize His authority in our life?
The first thing is we need to recognize Jesus
God sent Jesus into our lives
To be our Lord and Savior
And not only is God far away
But God is close
He is a personal God
Islam, Allah is far away
We can't reach Him
That's why they have to pray five times a day
That's why they have to go to Mecca
So that they can hopefully please God
But no, our God, God, the Father
God of Jacob, Abraham, Jacob and Isaac
He is a personal God
Because God sent Jesus to be with us
The Lord became flesh and lived among us
He is a personal God
He knows you
He knows what you're doing
He knows if you're giving Him your full worship
He is a personal God
Do you recognize Him?
If we come to worship today
We should be in awe
When we are singing the songs
We should be in awe of the Lord
God, You are amazing
We are praising You for who You are
We should be in reverence of Him
When we read His Word
And we recognize who God is
And what He's done in our life
We should be respecting and revering Him
And we should recognize His authority
And His promises
As we read the Word of God together
The second thing we need to do
Is humble ourselves
謙卑我們自己
驕傲人
驕傲的人學不學到東西
會不會學東西
不會的
謙卑的人才會學東西
Humble ourselves
Fear of the Lord
Means that we humble ourselves before the Lord
I don't know
But I know who knows
And God knows
我不知道
我不懂
但我知道神會帶領我的
神是有智慧的
祂會帶領我們的
We need to humble ourselves
謙卑我們自己
第三樣東西
We need to pray for wisdom
Are you praying for wisdom?
Vienne prayed for wisdom
In her school work
是不是
She's still praying for wisdom
In her school work
Are you praying for wisdom
In your school work
In your relationships
With your family
你有沒有求神
給你有智慧
在你不同的方面
Life的不同的難處
And the last thing is
Not only we need to know wisdom
We need to what
Do wisely
We need to obey God's wisdom
如果神是提醒你
給你有智慧
你做不做到呢
That is the next thing
Solomon 做不做到呢
He was the wisest person in the world
他很有智慧
他很有名有智慧
神給了他智慧
但為什麼他有這麼多老婆呢
有幾多個
七百個老婆
還有三百個同胞
為什麼
Because he fell into temptation
He knew the wisdom of the Lord
He was not obeying the Lord
There is a difference
Between knowing wisdom
And following God's wisdom
我們認識神的智慧
但我們會不會obey
祂的智慧呢
Are we gonna obey God's wisdom
For example
很多次
我們有個弟兄
在我們的團契
我們很多次跟他說
你等一下吧
這個女朋友還沒信主
你為她祈禱吧
希望她信了主
然後才有約會
因為基督徒應該約會其他基督徒
Light 和 Darkness 何來
這是Paul 說的
但他有沒有聽
他沒有聽
那又怎樣
他們約會了
慢慢就沒有認識神
就沒有回教會
你知道智慧
但你有沒有obey
這兩個是不同的東西
我講一個故事
我的朋友在多倫多
他的爸爸
他很喜歡怎樣
他很喜歡賭錢
He was obsessed with gambling
It could be stocks
It could be whatever
那些家庭就勸他
不要啦
你不要賭啦
不要賭在你不知道的股票裡
你太大風險了
你現在在做什麼
他就
他把家庭的錢都賠了
他們被賠了
他們要賣了房子
要搬到更小的房子
因為這個原因
他知道神的智慧
他不應該被錢所迫
他知道智慧
但他沒有obey
而這個結果
The family suffered
You might know the wisdom
But you need to obey the wisdom of the lord
We need to pray to god
That he helps us
你越來越大
你就會知道
You keep making the same mistakes
Over and over again
我們越來越大
We make the same mistakes over and over again
搞錯,我又這樣,我又這樣
We need to listen to god's wisdom
我們一起起來
請各位請幾位上來
Let us take a moment right now
To ask god for wisdom in our life
我們一起閉上眼
Let's have all eyes closed
I want you to pray for wisdom in your life right now
In whatever area
It could be your family
It could be your mental health
It could be your school work
It could be conflict with your friends
Pray for wisdom right now
And pray that you would have the obedience
To follow god's wisdom
我們一起祈禱
God, we humble ourselves before you
We are in awe of who you are
We recognize you are the most powerful
All-knowing creator of this world
And we ask for wisdom in our life
Many times we make mistakes
We don't know what to do
But we trust you
Because we know you know
What is best for us
And we trust your plan
Give us wisdom in our life, lord
And not only wisdom of knowledge
But the wisdom to obey you
In everything you call us to do
In jesus' name we pray, amen
(音樂停止)